[Music]
so hello there this is my friend Stephen
and I'm Andrew Sweeney and Stephen Lewis
and we're going to talk about feminism
we're in trouble already
yes we're already in trouble with the
beginning of modernity with the change
of Technology in Western world with the
with the with the development of new
tools there was a change and a and and
this has changed the change in gender
relations which only became more
accentuated through the centuries of
modernity and only began to reverse
itself around the in turn of 20s you
know beginning of the 20th century maybe
in the 19th century somewhere around
there but okay so we're talking about
the power dynamics between men and women
correct okay so so there's a there's a
presentation I've thinking about this
for a long time I there was a I had a
philosophy professor who said that back
in the Middle Ages women were in control
of family men were in control of the
state and this got me thinking for years
and years also think about this and
never heard a voice she's podcaster and
she said it in a she said something very
simple she said that men and women
working in the fields in late in the
Middle Ages basically did equal work
they worked alongside of each other and
let's not forget that women were often
pregnant when they were working and then
in the late Middle Ages there there
began to be changes in the tools that
were being used such as the plow for
example and these were bigger tools
which were not it simply wasn't a good
idea for women to use them so men it's
interesting this on the side you said
the plow and that's that's a very
phallic but it was big
took a certain type of you know it was
basically easier for men to manage
certain tools which and maybe we're
bigger they were herded a man they
weren't really hard at matters but
they'd they had different demands and
and this began because of this there
began a separation of of gender
attachment just to tools and and and the
most important thing to take note of
here is that the women I'm guessing were
were behind this in other words they
endorsed it and the reason is the tools
were more productive there was they
produced more food for example so there
was a good it was a reason for there to
be a gen during of tools because it
involved greater prosperity and it's in
the late Middle Ages that you see ink a
gret very very small increases in
prosperity which gradually increased up
through the through the 16th and 17th
centuries and then in the in the 19th
century and 18th centuries in the 19th
century there's a significant increase
in prosperity and this is all related to
the technology now it wasn't something
it wasn't problematic I mean the reason
why Charles Dickens wrote about urban
poverty stuff is because it was creating
lots of social havoc if the world was
changing it was changing quickly and but
nonetheless there was an increase in
prosperity related to technology and
this carried on right after the 20th
century us parity just completely
skyrocketed in 20th century but at the
same time towards the end of the 19th
century and accelerating into the 20th
century various other tools changed
changed the way of life for women so
that there was a there was a balancing
out of this I I guess what I what I
imagine is that there was a an inflation
of male status based on on the fact that
they were using
more productive tools then then more and
more productive in the sense that they
produced great more food scalable yes
yeah that's a scalable technology rather
than just domestic technology right
exactly and that had status because it
meant that they there was less
starvation you know there was it was
less hardship so this this involved a an
inflation of male status through those
centuries accelerating up into the 20th
century but nonetheless being balanced
out by the mention of other technologies
which enabled women to acquire a similar
survey something similar about to to
acquire another kind of liberation if
you will from from from the toils of
life so I mean the whole the whole
universe of domestic equipment such as
you know and geez there's no end to even
running water for example running water
is enormous you know there's all kinds
of things that we we don't even think
about you know and stuff like tampons
and this stuff nobody thinks about how
important they are but but awesome there
are obvious things like dishwashers
refrigerators and centralized heating
you know you didn't have to go out and
cut wood this there's no end to all do
to along this of domestic technology
which bit-by-bit
gave women a different different quality
of life from what they had you know on
New Year's previous this happen
I just have a thought I was thinking
that oh yeah there's there's a sense
that that that leads to liberation of
women but then I have thought that you
know all those domestic chores actually
create community infant son in some oh
my god some way and and and that women
suddenly become isolated in the kitchen
right in the 1950s America you know
Mormons to be seems to be an interesting
kind of missing piece in all this this
story right that prosperity and between
quotes liberation
is is simultaneous to alienation and I
put incalculable
loss of quality of qualitative life and
and even you might say socio-cultural
catastrophe yeah so there's more people
taking antidepressants and that kind of
thing you know and popping pills and
whatever no just depression in general
so we're taking we're taking stock of
the fact that we're you know we no
longer have slaves and we are no longer
slaves and we're not starving and at the
same time we are completely alienated
lost you know over waste and and depress
like you say there's so there's this
dichotomy of amazing achievement you
know place next to terrible loss and so
this is this is basically if we're to
understand the technological revolution
we really have to think about these both
these at once and try and very slowly
sit through makes sense what it is you
know people who feel the loss tend to
condemn the technological revolution and
people who feel the prosperity tend to
understate the loss and yeah so we're in
both the trick is to is to go through a
tray slowly and to and to acknowledge
both and try and work out what the issue
is I I absolutely agree the loss the
community is enormous and that it could
be argued that the technological
revolution I mean the blossom I think
for example that community is arguably a
female thing it's it's arguably female
dominators I said a few minutes back
that family in the Middle Ages was a
female dominant female were on a female
dominant arguably the closest synonym we
have to family medieval family is
community because what we think of as
family today is nothing like the
medieval family which was like a massive
bunch of people you know all sort of
blood and send me blood related you know
you're looking at nice you know the
nuclear family has its has its
you know pathologies as well right oh
yeah oh yeah that's also I think the
nuclear family is very very young it's
almost yeah I mean that's a whole other
feature of didn't exist before the 19th
century I believe the nuclear family
there was no such thing as a regular
family in there well there was there was
such a thing as monogamous families in
other words you had the same mother and
father and your brother and sisters have
same mother fucker that seems they go
back to simply go back aways and so but
nonetheless the kids were raised in a
village with a whole bunch of other kids
so they weren't raised in the house only
by two parents they were raised by all
kinds be ya know they're you know the
old cliche or proverb that it takes a
village to raise a kid to raise a child
I mean that's very profound I think it's
very it's very true statements and I
think for our back children were raised
by communities they were very much
raised by when I was even when I was a
kid you know there were constantly
strangers yelling at me you know there
was this constant and they weren't only
doing they were only yelling at me they
would be saying although it was a much
more there was much more communication
between all adults and children when I
was oh yeah that's why perhaps our
parents could let us go run on out on
the streets for hours because because
there was an understanding perhaps that
there would be some feedback from you
know the neighbors or so I think I think
community in many ways is that you know
the whole the way that women roll you
know they seem to be much more people
oriented man they're the whole the whole
gossip culture is is on a positive level
it's it's really making of community
it's you know that everybody they know
about people they don't want people in
you know there's this network of people
knowing about each other or women
knowing about these these hundreds of
donor to people right and and so that's
the kind of it's the making of community
and it does seem to me that that has
been I mean it's
it's kind of obvious that it's been it's
been disintegrating and very quickly
zoats
perhaps perhaps we've we've gotten
reached the bottom and it's not gonna
get any worse because I don't know how
it can get any more so maybe people are
gonna you know start getting out of the
houses again and talking to neighbors
and stuff who knows well you live in
Newfoundland and you would think a
newfoundland would be more community
oriented there's definitely I mean where
I am like embarrassment I'm an extreme
example I stare I stare away from this
is a social town so was going to say
yeah I think that the lossy community is
very much related to the technological
revolution and so that arguably so
arguably the technology is kind of a
male-dominated phenomenon and it's only
been recently reversing you know
arguably tools are male in a sense okay
so I was reading something this morning
on Twitter by a guy named Alexander bard
and it was a quote and he said something
like okay so you want that to destroy
the the patriarchy and he said two world
wars okay
seventy million soldiers all men you
know killed destroyed right it's already
been destroyed the patriarchy right
anyway I thought that was an interesting
statement I wanted to bring it up
because you're talking about male tools
and obviously obviously war is is you
know has been dominated by men and male
tools you're bringing you just
introduced I think another subject right
now which is the subject of maleness and
sought and its relationship to
sovereignty it seems to me that probably
the greatest impetus for the development
of technology was sovereignty in other
words protecting your lands from from
invasion
and from from the enemy from the outside
and it does also seem to bear Leo be
estat the war is something which seems
to be very quickly moving towards
something like redundancy in other words
you know and when nuclear arms
especially it makes this obvious but
also conventional arms or have become so
deadly so effective that people people
are not very inclined to go to war no I
you know there's still Wars happening
but way less than you used to be and all
it takes really it seems to me is for
the for the whole world to be armed with
drones and it seems to me that's only a
matter of time before most that most the
world's countries have have lots of
effective you know drones and then we
the war is going to be taken over by
robots basically yeah something like
that
and it'll also make war we don't in
other words the the necessity to prepare
for war which was essentially mail thing
seems to be redundant it's we're getting
there anyway and that that is a very
alienating thing for men because they
had such an important role which was to
protect the communities of their
territory protecting women so some
people might say that this means that
the matriarchy is rising right and and
and so that now we're going to we're
living through a more of a matriarchal
time as opposed to a patriarchal time
like the 20th century was male-dominated
in the Senate in that sense right and
the 21st century and it will be female
dominated what do you think about that
as a as a it's possible it's quite
possibly true there is one extremely
there's there's one very big danger that
I worry about a great deal which is how
should I put it well this is related to
Freud who's got reputable ism and it's
it's you know the the male who has who
is lost who doesn't
have a purpose you know is I mean to put
it bluntly is not only is he pathetic
but he's just inclined suck on his
mama's tit I mean there's he he he won't
grow up and he will not only not grow up
he will become a burden be taken care of
that's already happening and that's that
I think I mean that's the infantile
society that's the internet right
whether or not we are becoming
matriarchal is irrelevant to the fact
that we absolutely have to figure out
ways to get males to develop and to
become men and to become you know and to
pursue and find a purpose in life and to
get on with it
and so that that kind of renders the
question our will becoming matriarchal a
little bit much I think you know this is
a it's a necessity for this to happen
and that's my take on that but it may be
the case that were we're swinging it
seems to me we're in a female-dominated
age anyway that may not be a bad thing
provided that men are not for one
heinous which is one of my biggest
issues with feminism and two that
they're not that they're that they're
developing in their developing property
and becoming men and what doesn't matter
so what does it mean to develop
masculinity in the in the 21st century
as opposed to what it was in the 19th
century or they're you know or the
Middle Ages are well that's a very good
question so what does masculinity mean
today like I have a sense that it's
equally important you know I mean that's
a truism to femininity let the two are
complementary and would you have to be
fully developed to the hilt right right
it's true less strong men and strong
women not us not domineering women and
and pathetic man or or or you know or
you know alpha men and and and whatever
you know I defined for myself
what I call the gentleman the the
evolution of men is it I mean I learned
I've thought a lot about this in the
past year and it was related to you know
all this learning about psychometrics
through people like Jordan Pederson
tremendous drug preachers and others as
well that Karen strong and prepped month
on and a few others the my definition of
the gentleman which is what we should be
working on it has five points
responsibilities in culture confidence
integrity and there's always a fifth I
always forget the fifth responsibility
competence culture in other words you
you know if you don't know if you don't
know your literature you got at least
know your hockey scores there's there's
there's culture for every level of male
yeah and so he needs he needs to have
he's gotta have culture gone so
competence culture integrity
responsibility and so something like
that
points points us in a direction to for
men to look at what they need to do to
you know they have to fulfill these
criteria you know what do men do in the
face of the female principle is a it's a
kind of beginning question of mine in my
mind so the complete you know the
complete individual integrates both the
me meant the for male and female
principals into him or her mmm-hmm and
so if you're a man then you you have to
integrate the female principle into you
and the same thing for women and this
it's arguably the individual is someone
who who transcends the well you have to
integrate but but not be dominated by it
like that's animus the anima is is when
you're dominated with when a male is
dominated by the female the unconscious
female spirit and the Animus is when you
know you know there's this there's this
hyper masculinity that develops in a
woman you know
we put that on there but we've talked
about this already but but it's obvious
that a woman has to develop assertive
male qualities to survive in the world
and that's obvious that a man has to
develop you know certain certain caring
you know classically female qualities I
think there's also something you wrote
up prior to modernity sovereignty and
community dyad okay
now maybe you want that was the second
one and you've already talked a little
bit about sovereignty and community so
maybe maybe you want to go over that a
little bit okay yeah that relates to
what I said men were in charge of the
state women in charge of community
there's one big feminist argument is
that they weren't allowed to have
property I think that I think a closer
analysis of that shows that property was
a something very much tied to
sovereignty you know and so sovereignty
first of all the Kings at the top but
really everything is sovereignty is
compartmentalize right down to the
bottom and this is part of the basically
the protection of the security of a
place it allows it to be managed the
land and it keeps it strong against as a
as a bulwark against the enemy the enemy
on the outside and this allows for
community inside it to thrive and so
this is a this is a dyad what I mean
that's a yin-yang dynamic and so so to
be primarily concerned with security to
end the end and that is primarily a
concern of order which permeates the
entire territory and allows for all
other things all other engagements other
interactions too to just freely freely
move about inside the context of
sovereignty I don't like to wear
patriarchy I think that's a it's a it's
a sort of a hateful feminist word and
it's born from out of out of a filial
perception of men because patriarchy it
seems to me is basically means some sort
of lineage
inside larger extended families of the
past that's kind of what it means seems
to me so aunts and uncles and in the you
know grandfathers and and there might
have been a power there might have been
a particular man in a large or extended
family who was more have more respect
who was not a jerk the Patriot that's
right and so it's a it's a totally
filial not totally family centered
centered lens on men in other words it's
a female it's a female center lens on
men it's not that interesting
sovereignty is the interesting one
because if if if you don't protect your
turf then the enemy will invade the
person who I really understood this
through the the black conservative
writer Thomas Sol in a chapter called
called a brief history of slavery I
think it's in the book
black rednecks white liberals and he
talks about how the abolition of slavery
was really preceded by the development
of sovereignty inside in Europe and
basically this is a fascinating video
history I had I had no idea of this the
Europe is exclusively responsible for
the abolition of slavery in the world
now they're still slaves but you know
basically at one time every corner of
the earth had slaves everything was
slavery was big was here there was
slavery slaves and Buddhist monasteries
in Tibet and for example and then the
Europeans what they did they they
developed regional sovereignty in Europe
and they which allowed them to keep the
out the the the tribes next door from
invading them all the time and abducting
people for slaves to take them as laves
and then once they discovered the great
virtues of no longer being enslaved and
they and they related this to
sovereignty and they their sovereignty
this was also simultaneous toric lee to
the great burgeoning of the of European
imperial power and so they took this
recognition of benefit from you know not
allowing themselves to be means late
turned imposed its abolition on the rest
of the world through their imperial
measures and the word thomas ola says
that there were no economic incentives
for this it was simply a moral
imperative which grew out of European
imperialism which grew out of European
sovereignty so sovereignty abolished
slavery and sovereignty it didn't just
abolish slavery it achieved a whole
bunch of other things too so anybody who
thinks that men were were I mean this is
all in other words this was all a
function of the further development of
the male principle and it would seem to
me that the notion of sovereignty and it
will always be important someone said to
me the other day it was true but I do
like the paradox I just a feminism isn't
it I mean all of these things that
liberated the woman you know were
firstly developed by men you know which
is so men are men are actually
interested in the liberation of women
right absolutely so so so all the other
you know all the medicine all the you
know politics and stuff is was so so the
liberation of women is not just women
liberating themselves from men it's men
and women together liberating women
absolutely and the during the enduring I
don't know what the word is hanging I
suppose of feminism about them being
second second-class or something is to
me completely abominable and they they
don't seem to they seem not to they seem
to be willfully denying this process
which led to why is this happening
what's what's what's baby hunt and
Beyond behind that like I I think they
just like condemn it and say oh you know
those bad feminists you know those
extreme feminists like what why is this
why is why is this so all pervasive you
know why is it so awkward why is this
sort of I said in this Andry right
because it feels like misandry it's like
why is it so all pervasive at this at
this time
well one I mean I thought I already
discussed the the inflation of the male
status turn because of technology and
that's I think that involved so they're
not this there was a really a separation
of status but prosperity came with it so
there was kind of an endorsement from
women so I think there's a resentment of
that what a thing is not only not only
covered in relatively short period of
history and I think in the 20th century
correct himself well so there's a
resentment over that period of history
which I suppose you could argue is
understandable but then I think they
also feminists of also conflated the
notion and this is where we can talk
about agency and hypo agency the the
idea that women don't mm-hmm haven't
really had a voice in history well I
think there's there's strong evidence
that female hypo agency is is something
that worked for them for a long time now
the fact that they went hypo agency is I
think I have a general idea of it it's
sort of the sense that one one not only
does not a voice but doesn't doesn't
need to have a voice in other words
doesn't need to articulate doesn't it
doesn't particulate one selves and so
it's like you're the power behind the
throne kind of thing right something
like that yeah
doesn't have a public voice and nor does
nor does she in this case have a desire
to have a public voice there's a
Thursday and a kind of a sense of which
it works for you know and this it would
appear that this is there's lots of
women who want to have a public voice I
have absolutely no issue with that
that's fine but it would seem to me that
the women who choose to have a public
voice and who pursue it will always be a
minority they may well be an important
minority but they and there's a real
case that maybe feminism in recent years
is a case from the important
of women who wish to to have a voice
which death agency we should do
publication and that's fine I mean
that's it's more than fun it's important
that anybody who wishes to have public
agency should should choose with us
because we're complex and there's all
kinds of different types of people with
different capacities and yeah there's a
you know some some women are very if I
can say so very masculine you know and
that's why and there's no problem with
different types of people I mean but in
terms of averages there's no reason why
they should where everything should be
equalized in some kind of a way because
part of the reason for whatever
imbalances there are is is if preference
and choice and and what people actually
want to do right that's this was
explained best to me in a fantastic talk
by Karen strong about this very subject
female hypo is just fantastic
Wow she was missing inclusionary
psychology but basically the majority of
women are not going to want to have
public agency they're perfectly happy to
have to live more discrete lives you
know in in the company of their friends
in the in the realm of their families
and friends and and not to expand their
their voice beyond that reach and and
that's where and it's see I'm winning
I'm perfectly willing to put my neck out
and say that that's winning no your
man's bleeding Steven they're perfectly
willing your women mansplaining I'm
pretty confident about this look they're
gonna they're gonna be this way that's
what they bring us what they like that's
what they prefer and there was there
will be an important minority who won't
be that way so and Karen explains this
in evolutionary terms the the the
discrete woman
first of all she
quietly she heard she did not attract a
lot of attention she was not given she
was she was kept in a safer zone by
being so and the expressive man was was
you know it was evolutionary advantage
from the point of view of procreation
that means passing on his genes to be to
live dangerously to be out in the world
to be picking his neck out in all kinds
of different ways and that's what agency
really is you're constantly taking
chances you and your you don't you know
if you if you have the public life
you're always you know putting your foot
in your mouth so to speak you have to
that's what public life is you're
constantly in this in this dangerous
world and and not only so so the minute
that is the separation between age dizzy
and hypo agency the woman hangs pegs
around the hearth and this will increase
the probability that she will pass on
the her genes she's her her importance
around young children as extremely is
very high she had to remain safe in
order to to children to survive to
adulthood so as to pass on their genes
and the man all he had to do was
impregnate the woman and then he could
be killed a few days later you know off
doing some dangerous thing and so this
was a both it was an evolution from the
point of view of passing on your genes
it was an evolutionary advantage for
both genders mm-hmm when I was listening
to Brett Weinstein talk about that he
was he was talking about that as this is
you know this is this is a truth right
about biology right but we have to kind
of overcome that because biology is
tyrannical my biology is terrible like
it as it in the sense of how it works
without let's say a human consciousness
intervening aware of biological
biologically determining factors in the
human condition so most definitely I'm
most definitely believed in society I
absolutely believe in social construct
these are these are absolutely these are
clear to me I also believe in the
intervention of reasoning which is all
other set of that's a whole other realm
of interaction you know intellect
intellect so the intellectual the social
biologically exist hierarchy so yeah no
no no I'm not saying that I'm not a
biological determinist but I am saying
that these predispositions exist which
mean that women will remain will
continue to seek out avenues of hi-po
agency inside the social constructs that
we that we have no matter no matter how
liberating they are yeah it's funny how
there's a difference between ideology
and actual behavior right I mean I mean
what am I trying to say it seems like it
seems like yes we human beings are not
conscious enough right generally to
behave you know in an enlightened manner
right they're still they're still we're
still in the darkness right we're still
we're still we're still we're so 90
percent unconscious I mean most of us so
all of these will happen no matter what
our ideological your constructs we put
we put on we overlay exactly and it also
may not be desirable for the mean for us
to be on every sane conscious that might
be that we just don't sane maybe we're
only designed to have this little
trickle of consciousness going through
reality so that we can actually learn
things or whatever it's so so the rest
of us is just on autopilot and so that
kind of explained it's a lot of this
predisposition stuff right and so you
know like yeah so that's that their
theory lies the argument further for
predisposition we rely on our
predisposition so that we can
consciously do some tiny little thing
right yeah so do you want me to look at
the list again
oh yeah sexual violence and sexual
attraction that's interesting well okay
this guy let me can I start that off
okay what's the difference between
ravishing in an enlightened way and like
let's say rape yeah you're a swell
[Music]
this is another evolutionary psychology
argument because women are women are
seem to be desperate to be safe and to
make rules at this point in history it's
like who want so many rules just to make
sure that you know that you don't
transgress this this this space right
there is something in a rather system
that has to be about transgression I
mean on some level so so so you know
are we moving towards a you know sexual
police state or you know like like
what's going on yeah that's just I mean
I was gonna say about this was about me
- for example was was precisely this
subject of violence in sex it does seem
to me that violence is inextricable from
from sex and and the reason is totally
unconscious
although the benefits were evolutionary
and that means that women who were
attracted to more dangerous men violent
men were men who were capable / verbally
speaking of her living themselves and a
saber-toothed tiger and while he was
being while he was being dragged away
and eat and she had time to get away
with the baby so to speak this this
that's a rational interpretation in
other words she's actually thinking oh
if I if I if I if I mate with him then
then I'll be able to get away from the
saber-tooth Tiger but that's not it it's
it's way more unconscious than that it's
totally unconscious the women who were
attracted to these these dangerous and
crazy men who were fearless they they
passed on their genes more and the women
who were attracted to gentle submissive
men
whoo okay we do what they were told so
the men who are out doing dangerous
things hurling themselves that dangerous
animals and fighting off a dangerous man
and whatever they passed on their genes
and the and the women who were attracted
to those men passed on their genes more
and so the criteria of sexual attraction
even sexual attraction to the edgy man
to very to a whole variety of what I
would bluntly call violence in men is
evolution to the beast like beauty and
that's again the beauty and the beauty
right so women the ultimate female
erotic fantasy is to is detain the
monster is to first of all attract the
monster and then to have him on her side
she won't hurt her Mian well she won't
her the the monster won't hurt her
because he loves her but but but he's a
fucking monster yes but and she that's
it that's her erotic fantasy to me the I
was thinking about it recently the
probably the most the height of female
erotica is the is the Silence of the
Lambs where the Jodie Foster character
is in conversation with Hannibal the
cannibal and the reason why she's an
investigator she's she's looking she's
trying to understand this other serial
killer and she's using him to help her
understand it understand them and in the
process they developed this periodic
interchange and in it there's a given
moment in that film where she realizes
that she's found a place in his heart
and that he will never hurt her and
that's like and and she's totally
disturbed by this because she said she's
had this her body is in total
arousal bias and she knows that he's in
Currys the craziest darkest serial
killer out there you know Hannibal the
cannibal but at the same time she knows
that she's safe in his company and that
is that's like completely so it's taming
the predator right it's yeah it's aiming
the uber predator or the you know the
most dangerous man right
so this this cut this I think this is a
very important insight in in critiquing
the me to movement because there's a
performative contradiction here women
are to be fair they don't know it's
totally unconscious why am i attracted
to this man why why my truck - like and
so they're drawn to him they're drawn to
him they you know they end up getting
closed doors and then you know they're
they're very surprised by what happens
and so this this these fifty shades of
gray inside sexuality their attraction
to this and their desire to their their
temptation to enter into that world so
as to take to tame him so that's and
this and it's let's be fair here this is
these are these are deeply unconscious
draws this is not this is not something
that's she's ready it's not something
that she's reasoning in her these are
and see male male sexuality is not super
where we're most attracted to
sixteen-year-old girls and the reason is
being created back in time it increases
the chance that she will live long
enough to raise children best live long
enough to pass on her genes
that's it's you know it it would be many
ways way more intelligent to to I mean
there's all kinds of real arguments to
be attracted to it what wise are more
seasoned in many ways far more beautiful
woman whose but there's something about
this this teenage this teenage blossom
blossoming female which which completely
in a totally unconscious way grabs the
male and that it's you know so that's so
these are both completely irrational
well maybe the point here is is is
agency and and the point is agency and
responsibility and and blame and all of
that right yeah so so so it seems that
the me to movement is entirely has
entirely been based on blaming you know
pathological men and then you have a few
pathological men who are really bad and
they're obviously really bad and then
you blame everybody all men you know
all men sort of you know and most most
most you know people like me and you are
kind of you know ordinary guys you know
on don't are somewhat offended by it by
being you know put into that I say
pathology of just because you know we we
we have you know the male erection right
it's like the lack of perspective on
this this particular is this dimension
of violence and sex that that the lack
of perspective on that it just
infuriates me and the the hypocrisy of
it just you know
well maybe see is it the idea that sex
is dangerous right it's like it's not
just something you like you just like
cook up you know and you're a little
oven that's like it's it's a dangerous
game well it also it wasn't for nothing
that we put it in a cage on a leash a
long time ago it's not for nothing that
we have just do we have marriage you
mean they have this checks and balances
so as to contain sexuality so it's not
it's an old story that sexuality is a
beast and and sort of that pandora boxx
isn't it it's like yeah well like this i
mean learning about this female
attraction to to to to
minotaurs and werewolves and vampires it
was a major revelation to me it just it
was just completely it was it was it the
absolute eureka and actually this is
another feature in the feminist critique
where they're dead wrong
there could picture are key because or
basically most attracted to a cocktail
of status and the capacity not
necessarily violence but the capacity
for violence and then it was the
capacity for violence
combined with status eat is the pinnacle
she and the capacity for violence
doesn't mean one is going to use
violence but but but but but yes well
men should train in martial arts to be
highly dangerous i mean that's that's
masculine development that should you
that should be in school you know
I men women should woman should also
train you know I think female historical
affirmation of sovereignty through
sexual selection male historical
affirmation of community through
security okay so I'm glad because that
moves the discussion of sexual violence
and sexual attraction moves very cleanly
into the discussion of sovereignty
mmm-hmm the women are the basically are
in control of sexual selection and
that's been demonstrated by genetics by
evolutionary biology they I mean I they
don't figure this out but you know twice
as many women pass on their genes as men
something like 80% of women pass on
their genes and only which is it's still
a statistic that I haven't recovered
from 40% 40% of men only pass on the
genes I'm going way back over time back
back through the back through the
millennia and that's a that's a stunning
statistic I don't know but a points to
women being a and since the criteria of
sexual selection is there it mean if if
there were no court or criteria of
sexual selection will mean that women
were kind of enslaved by a few number of
men or something bad but since the
criterion of sexual selection in other
words they're attracted to this combo of
violence and status is there it means
that they've had a role in sexual
selection and since they're twice as
they they're there they pass on their
genes twice as much it points to women
being in control of sexual selection
it's their it's their field it's their
round men men get chosen so to speak you
know they try to they struggle to get
chosen and women women are in control of
the elbe of the choosing and not the men
and you know women women make the final
decision so to speak and and there's
lots of good reason for this they're the
ones actually the revenue we're going to
have the children so that's a it makes
sense that that they be in control of
that it's
pretty stunning thing to learn that only
4% men pass on the keys
but anyway what that means is that they
had been women have been for countless
millennia selecting this male trait of
capacity for violence and status you
know greater confidence to know whatever
whatever big status you know and well
this basically is the this basically is
what has reinforced the the social
structures of sovereignty among this is
in other words female sexual selection
is the reinforcing factor of sovereignty
it is you know it breeds sovereignty so
to speak and so this idea that soy
breeds let's say can we can we unpack
the sword sovereignty a bit it breeds
individualistic strong-willed men or it
also breeds minded men who can function
well the militaries and that kind of
stuff competence but also breeds it has
it has a negative after-effects such as
violence towards women and men beating
down their women and telling them
they're second-class citizens it has
this it has this negative as well but
but it's it it could despite the
negative
it was bred into the men that that
disposition was bred into them the men
by female sexual selection you see what
I'm saying so this and this is all
ultimately unconscious so the idea that
men have kept women down is not quite
right because women have been choosing
this type of man who will assert himself
and power well it always seems like men
have a certain kind of hubris about
being in control but they're not always
in control like you know you see a guy
and his wife and the guys always being
you know he's always he's always in a
lesser sort of you know looming roles of
his wife he I see that a lot I see a lot
of men are very very very much
emotionally controlled by their by their
wives you know
so so they that's very that's very
you're not even allowed to talk about
that because the whole emphasis is on is
on men controlling women but but seems
to be that the reverse is true that
there is a there is a power dynamic
that's working but both ways and the
only real difference is is I guess is I
guess male physical strength and
capacity for before for for for violence
but I mean in 10 you know but
pathological violence right but yeah
otherwise this business of male female
power dynamics in relation I don't need
money like that's such a messy subject I
don't go there but I totally agree I
don't lead true you know female powers
very psychological and they will powers
physical and it's well I think one of
the one of the aspects of female power
is to constantly deny key male power and
yeah and that's a psychological that's
just not growing up fully yeah you know
not being a fully grown person to be
able to take responsibility for your
entire for your behavior you know and
your emotionality the like Camille
Talia's desire to make women strong
women is to you know get over that kind
of bullshit it's it is it is absolutely
dry of course there are people snow men
two victims in the world
there's minimum men and women die I am
totally convinced that women do not have
number men by the way in victim each in
the world in you know there are there
are many male victims as female victims
I believe in the world so that's another
feature of feminism which I find
repulsive you know they're constantly
going on about female victims and they
don't seem don't seem acknowledge the
fact that men are victims yeah so I
don't believe for one second that women
outnumber men as victims in the world I
don't believe for one second so but
that's another that's another and of
course you'll never it's impossible to
establish look well no no it's but it's
not an either-or kind of thing if a
woman's a victim
the victim it's like you know in Saudi
Arabia the men are victims because
because they put all their women in in
potato sacks it's like you know I don't
know how to say that but and maybe the
women are victims to be there they're
both victims
Branko codependency victimology is is is
goes both ways right so the real trick
is for people to be filled fulfill the
potential everybody and then when people
whose potential is fulfilled they you
you you get the sense of the fullness of
life a very dynamic they're expressing
right there you can you know like life
is full and that's you know you can tell
when someone is we have a pretty good
sense of when someone is not trying
whether they're male or female and it's
that third task is to be cool about the
business of making people thrive
including ourselves
so it's very simple approach the
question is that what makes men thrive
and what makes what makes women thrive
and is there a difference is the same
thing the psychometrics you know the big
five personality test and stuff that I
learned that was a major
iOpener and so that that was really
interesting man and more interested in
ideas women are more interested in
aesthetics you know many more certain
things will reverse did people these
these are the avenues of development in
other other there are other differences
too but the the you know those are those
are the biggies women are more neurotic
than men which means they're in it when
when rendered that's a kind of a
negative thing but when rendered on when
you turn that into a positive things it
means that they're more vigilant to
danger I think which is a form of
intelligence yeah Esper I was thinking
about that that's the positive aspect of
neuroticism is that a lot hyper-vigilant
correct and and looking out for
danger and so that's it intelligent
dominant one according to the big flat
just on a neurotic person and and I
think that I've drawn I was upset when I
first learned that but I've more or less
figured out that it has it's a huge part
of my intelligence son I'm constantly
seeking out possible dangers you know
and that's that's kind of how I roll
obviously it was a Seidel realm what
people are thinking and how the way you
know people are thinking could be
dangerous that kind of thing so that's
an erotic thing to be doing all the time
so that's good yeah so yeah so there are
different avenues of development I think
the traditional avenues like teaching
men like you said martial arts in terms
of how we can get out of this this big
swing right now where people people seem
to be asleep and especially men it
seemed to be asleep they seem to be
escapist how they can carry on you know
the word sovereignty I also think is
related to the to to individualism
becoming an individual becoming an
undivided soul and undivided being is is
to become a sovereign being though you
know its sovereignty really is
transforming rather than disappearing
its it there's a sense in which it is we
did turn a traditional sovereignty in
other words being able to fight wars is
now redundant but maybe there are mental
wars maybe there's psychological wars
you notice maybe there's wars against
poor health
maybe there's more was against the
environmental destruction he's you know
we can we sovereignty remains a an
extremely important thing is just that
its meaning is transformed it's no
longer the business of going off and
telling people but it might be the
business of killing has some some
killing bad ideas exactly something like
that or killing a killing conceptual
madness and
in the society or you know hunting just
taking somewhat of a risk taking someone
risk right taking men got make men more
inclined to take more risks yeah
the there was a great interview and you
probably heard it to David fuller
together honey where she talked about
the ash test now I only just know once I
was listening again we're trying to
understand it would be better but she
basically said that the ash test was
about in lis fifties or something it was
a test for conformism and they tested
they found that men were basically 75
percent conformist in it and it had to
do with they were they were asked these
questions they were able to see how the
people before them answered the question
it was kind of like a trick yeah I saw
that the first seven people before them
had answered the question in a certain
way so they were and and it was a trick
because the way the seven people before
them answered was wrong was the wrong
answer
and then they went ahead and gave the
same wrong answer so they and so they
were testing conformism they found that
men were very conformist and I think the
the percentage was seventy five percent
but then they did the test a number of
years later on women exclusively and
found that women were more conformed she
didn't say how much but it was a it was
a kind of a surprising results to the to
you know to that inquiry and so she well
it may it make sense it's it's logical I
mean if you're if you're a guy you're
physically stronger and so so you're
more likely to go out on a limb I mean
if you're a woman you you're you're the
you know you have to be hyper vigilant
about children and how people are and
then so so you you have that the rules
matter much more right whereas it
measures a man can sort of play around
with the rules you can amend men like to
do that they like to go it and could
have bend the rules a little bit but
here's here's my point women do too but
more men more right here's here's my
point
we think
being risk takers but the ash test shows
that most men are not oh yeah so in
other words it's a it's a small minority
of men
most men are conformist they don't want
to stick their neck out they want to fit
in
oh yeah and the ash tests also showed
that even more women are not that way so
in other words is not that men are the
risk that group takers it's just that no
but I mean there are more bits that
there are more men who are likely to
uncertainly women who would like to do
that as well wait we just have to get
over this problem with with there being
differences like there's differences so
what I mean you leave people alone you
don't judge if a man wants to be a house
you don't judge it it doesn't want to be
a hazard husband you leave them alone
and you don't judge it the same thing
with women if a woman wants to be out in
this out in the workforce and she wants
to hire a nanny to raise her kids then
that's her business business but hers
and and if she hold on hold on there
well maybe there there's a way in which
that's bad for children yes but if she
chose it here's the thing she is a she
she has agency she has free choice and
maybe maybe she'll marry man but the
truth is no we can criticize people for
being good and bad parents but the truth
is people have their disposition
maternal and she has children I mean you
got to live with that reality so it
might be better for the kid to be with
the nanny or something yeah we're saying
is things are complex but in other words
you but that doesn't mean that people
don't make bad choices
mean that you know we we have the usual
social pressures to make people behave a
little bit better when out where I was
pointing out is the another paradox of
feminism is that maternal ISM maternity
is is looked down upon right yes
and so the PERT though the woman who
wants to be a mother is is extremely
discriminated against often and and
can't really do that because because of
that however I do have something to say
about maternity which is a complex thing
and this screen this spring your
thoughts but I found very disturbing
facts so so man this is not the you know
arguably I've spent a lot of time
thinking about the eradication of child
mortality actually medication chocolate
charity is arguably the most important
human achievements period yeah if
anybody else wants to argue that there
is a more important human achievement
than fine but it would it's a pretty
strong argument that there's nothing
nothing matches that you know back not
that back in history damn good point
actually yeah not that far back in
history most kids died we didn't hurt
each other and that's a crazy and then
it ended this is actually a huge feature
of what we call female liberation it's
amazing how little it gets discussed I
mean they were very very busy
mostly failing to keep young children
alive for a long long time and they had
they were a major social machine that
was their role it was an enormous role
absolutely enormous role and then it
ended poof in a very in a very short
period of history it was obscured to be
fair to be fair to
the lack of recognition of his
achievement it was obscured by the wars
that happened during the the the you
know first happens when you century and
so that was a time of great great tumult
you know there was lots of reasons not
to be celebrating you know we should
have a week if not it's not several
weeks in the course of the year to for
festivities to celebrate the eradication
anyway so what happened and the
traditional female role was suddenly
enormously the grave role was suddenly
chopped down it was it just disappeared
and so speak if you want to talk about
the technological revolution in radical
alienation it seems to me that there is
in the loss of purpose so so loss of
purpose great a great alienation but
let's take this another step further
this is this is something that a very
disturbing regime on the Stars things
about this this is where its theory
Freud was very worried loved us he you
know with with their the loss of this
great role they were very very busy they
were also they they didn't add the
benefits of Washington she was a you
know vacuum cleaners and all these
things and centralized heating running
water so they were very busy they were
fuckin all funny and then all of a
sudden they have opens time and not only
that they don't have any children and
they survive well what do they do they /
mother them they because their maternal
drive has been cut down the devouring
mother is what you're talking about they
swallow up their children and well it's
because of the but it's because of
maternity which has alienated maternity
maternity it seems to me is best defined
as and we've we don't we don't think of
it this way it's best defined as the
urgent drive to keep young children from
perishing that's
that doesn't exist anymore well yeah it
does exist I see it in my wife all the
time it's very intense well it's now the
one child but but but but it's varied
it's still there yes it was not the
drivers only around for millennia and
all of a sudden it's no longer it's
redundant
and so it the drive is so strong that it
finds itself applying itself to all
sorts of other elements of life not just
to what the children of women but to
society to social welfare to all kinds
of things which involved and over
coddling of the human race Posehn you
might a child child mortality radication
girl and we're very confused about this
and we are it's a it's an addiction we
the men I think are most most easily
susceptible to this work we just we
can't get enough of this female love
this female but we treat our wives like
like mothers we we were completely
confused about this this maternal power
in women in both men and women are
confused about it and and this is
something that we we simply must get
over and how I don't I mean well I mean
maybe it's maybe it's women becoming
managers or something or moving into
this you know there was a there's a
thing in Iceland where so like when
there was an economic crash in Iceland
all of the the male companies they all
crashed and there was a few companies
that survived and they were all they
were all run by women because women are
better women were better at risk
management right they they they were
looking out for their employees they
were thinking about the future where men
were making impulsive decisions and
taking risks and I don't know I guess I
guess I guess this I guess this way
you're this drive this maternal drive
you're right it has to be it has to be
channeled into something in some other
it pathologically what it becomes is it
becomes another kind of witch-hunt I
think or
when it doesn't have a lose when it
doesn't have use it becomes very very
destructive of itself and others
well one argument about one of my
arguments feminist technology is that
they're angry because they were
liberated which is a which is a total
contradiction I would piss a few people
off too well
what is freedom let's say freedom
doesn't if you're liberated what are you
gonna do right that's the thing freedom
is not the whole story meaning and
responsibility that's the whole Jordan
Pederson thing to fill the void where
mere freedom you know because if we just
gave you freedom wait we're just we're
just gonna go crazy right yeah also have
to you know total freedom is something
like I mean freedom can be fun and
intent more intelligent ways but there
is a sense in which freedom simply means
nihilism just means nothing means
meaninglessness and that's that moment
that's a disturbing definition of
freedom that we have to very quickly get
past you know you visited her the brief
moment you see oh I don't want that no
responsibilities you know just get drunk
all the time on a beach trees or the
rest of my life I mean that's not nobody
it's more profound than that is that we
do have a lot of freedom rights we do
have a lot of freedom but but we have a
problem with meaning right yes use
problem
huge huge that's that's on both the male
and female side you know men have this
existential problem of meaning
I think women also have I think there's
a different nature to both both to the
meaning crisis right John Varick I think
his name is he talks about the zombie
you know the zombie craze right and the
zombie craze just it's just meaningless
it's people who have freedom but no
meaning and all they do is consume right
it's human brains and they consume
whatever and that's the that's the
pathology but
yeah yeah yeah no absolutely yeah once
again the the technological revolution
and its relationship to what we would
think of as traditional male and female
redundancy creates a brand-new reality
which is new that's a new reality
yeah male and female redundancy that's
yeah and traditional yeah but probably
better and traditional male and female
we don't see have been our products
technological revolution and this is and
this is enormous and we were reading
from it and it's it was further than
that it's it's human redundancy actually
it's like if you think about it's very
scary yeah it's like it's like the it
would be becomes a completely
unconscious sort of creature right and
as all of all of the work is or all of
the the functions you know become
redundant one of the good things about
this a I scared
which I'm terrified of is it may be such
a big problem that it'll it'll get men
and women just just stop I mean that
will you know it'll to collaborate to
close I just don't believe that first of
all women are more victims a greater
victims than men in history I don't
believe that for one second I
I believe that the burgeoning of male
status the the inflation of men that
came at a great price to men as much as
to women so the idea that men had it
good for a few centuries and limited I
mean there were centuries of
unprecedented war it was it there was it
was it was a totally imbalanced and
difficult difficult time
so it simply was the result of the
confusion rapid technological change and
which is continuing to this day to this
day we're very confused about
technological change and so so the fact
that men were in charge of political
power and this is somehow an injustice
is a another
misra it's just a misunderstanding the
power
I mean someone had to first of all
create and run political power and it's
actually a terrible responsibility
usually involves you know the king
usually gets his head cut off at the end
of his read so this this you know I
don't think many women envied that role
they saw exactly what it was they saw
the man training to go to war and then
you know exactly resentful that the men
were out there you know training on time
and then going off to war
so this is and it's only later when when
the the war redundancy begins to become
within view that begins its journey
towards men well you know if we want to
if we want to rescue it or salvage any
any part of feminism perhaps we this is
what my thought was is it you don't want
to throw the whole thing out because in
terms of in terms of in terms of the you
know of free choice and free everything
you know free free self-determination
for women that's there's it's a truism
to say right that that's you know we're
okay with that
it's just that it's just that the
resentment has to go it's like it seems
like it seems that this is there's this
politics of resentment that is so
utterly utterly utterly toxic
two relationships between my first say
I've heard say that we're in the age of
the female shadow and that's an
interesting way to look at it and and
that's a reason to be optimistic because
uh yeah because when you to be to be
passing through the age of between a
shadow is is to be in the process of
becoming aware of the female shadow and
then then they're passed again
yeah I agree with that III I think
that's what's happening that's that
sounds right to me like the female
shadow has to come out like it has to
come out yeah like a like otherwise it's
it's it's just guess it has to come out
and perhaps all this stuff is you know
me too etc it's it's sort of a necessary
sort of explosion of what has to come
out on some bands like it to displace
you know get together be strong and you
know and not engage in this they can
learn about it so as to understand you
know so as to see the way forward I mean
I had to this was hard this was really
hard on me there couple years ago I
really felt that there was a sense in
which I was being knocked down too much
and so what looks like learned the
biology of women that was a major I open
it and then I could see that this was
going to this was gonna blow all or he's
gonna pass yet entrenched in some Dark
Age which which in which men don't
properly develop their never be terrible
thing if that happens and there's lots
of signs that men are improperly
developing today so in there is there's
there isn't
the necessity to criticize this and to
articulate the way forward for men and
women but you know men have to be able
to figure out how they can go forward in
this particular social climates the the
way is simply to develop your potential
find out who you are what your
capacities are and develop them
especially in an age of possible mass
redundancy work we don't see you know
you you should develop something even if
it doesn't pay you know let's say if
you're musical you should about yeah one
very very dangerous part of feminism is
the idea that the male psyche is so
patriarchal that he that his it is
completely lame like almost everything
he says is laden with with patriarchal
assumptions so so in other words
basically according to the feminists the
man the male psychological structure
basically needs to be dismantled so a
feminist not often this but but there
are feminists out there strong our core
feminists who see it as a moral
imperative to dismantle the male male
psychological structure which is
fundamentally pathological it is it is
so it will only create I know what it
will create I have the words for it it
will create hell on earth yes yes it's
there's nothing there is no that it's
one of the worst ideas that has ever
been and and there's a lot of feminists
who believe this and when I say
feminists like glued male feminists they
believe it and it's a very very bad idea
it's an absolutely miserable onion and
the way to counter that is to articulate
properly what the word sovereignty means
and then to also point out female sexual
selection is actually played an
extremely important role in the
and the reinforcements of sovereignty
over the generation after generation
throughout millennia
so it's in other words the women are
very they breed its sovereignty intimate
and this and and this is like benefit
this is ultimately a something very
beneficial to the to the human condition
provided that it is fully understood and
it's fully important